[Music]
according to the global burden of
disease study diets high in processed
meat like bacon ham hot dogs lunch meat
sausage may kill off more than a hundred
thousand people every year mostly due to
heart disease but also cancer and
diabetes
resulting in millions of healthy years
of life lost every year around the world
and it doesn't take much the union of
concerned scientists estimated that if
americans could cut down to an ounce a
week
thousands of annual cancer deaths could
be averted
but that's on a population scale
how can we better understand our
individual risk
though the nutrirex panel and the annals
of internal medicine meet papers i've
done the last few videos about discarded
their own findings using their numbers a
reduction in red and processed meat
consumption is associated with 13 lower
risk of premature death
what exactly does that mean like
what does a 13 increase risk of death
mean
to get a better handle on it let me
introduce the concept of microlives
acute risks such as riding a motorbike
or going skydiving may result in an
accident a good way to compare such
risks is with a unit known as a
micromort
defined as a one million chance of
sudden death i did a really fascinating
video about it recently however many
risks we take don't kill you straight
away think of all the you know lifestyle
frailties we get warned about such as uh
smoking drinking eating badly not
exercising and so on so the micro life
aims to make all these chronic risks
comparable
by showing how much life we lose on
average when we're exposed to them
a microlife is defined as 30 minutes of
your life expectancy
why is that well someone in their 20s a
22 year old man or a 26 year old woman
may have on average about 57 years left
that's about 20 000 days or 500 000
hours or a million half hours aha so
that's how they define a microlife a
reduction of one of the million half
hours we may have left
here are some things that would on
average cost a 30 year old man one micro
life
smoking two cigarettes
drinking two pints of beer or every day
they live 11 pounds overweight
see how helpful this can be in terms of
comparing risks so like drinking a pint
of strong beer cuts your life expectancy
short as much as smoking one cigarette
if it's unthinkable to you to have so
little respect for your own health that
you'd light up twice a day
maybe one cigarette in the morning one
at night then it should be just as
unthinkable being 11 pounds overweight
alternately you can compare life
extending behavior for example eating at
least five servings of fruits and
veggies a day may add an average of four
years onto your lifespan for men in
three years for women that's up to twice
as beneficial as exercising every day
but check it out exercise for 20 minutes
and you add an hour to your life two
microlives
so for all those who say they don't have
time to exercise
it's like a three to one return on
investment give 20 minutes of your life
to get 60 minutes of life
beyond that there's a bit of diminishing
returns but exercise an hour a day and
get back more time than you put in
okay
so what about the meat each burger is
associated with the loss of a microlife
so it's as if each burger we're taking
30 minutes off your life so lifespan
wise one burger appears equal to two
cigarettes
if it wouldn't occur to you to light up
at lunch maybe you should choose the
bean burrito instead
and processed meat is even worse there's
a couple of equivalent ways you could
say it uh imagine two people who are
identical in every way except that one
eats around 50 grams of processed meat a
day which is like one large sausage or
hot dog or a few strips of bacon and the
other eats none
eating that single serving of processed
meat every day is expected to take about
two years off the length of your life
two years less with your loved ones your
grandkids your spouse two more years of
mourning
or you could think about it on a
day-to-day basis eating a bologna or ham
sandwich every day just two slices of
deli meat is expected to take around one
hour off your life each day
don't think there's ever enough hours in
a day well you may have effectively one
less depending on what you pack for
lunch
alternately you could think about it in
terms of effective age eating 50 grams
of processed meat a day is expected to
add around two years onto your effective
age meaning basically give you the
annual chance of dying of someone two
years older
in summary wrote the chair of nutrition
at harvard and colleagues the neutral
rex meat recommendations suffer from
important methodological limitations and
involve misinterpretations of
nutritional evidence to improve human
and planetary health as a side bonus
dietary guidelines should continue to
emphasize dietary patterns low in red
and processed meats and high
in minimally processed plant foods such
as fruits vegetables whole grains nuts
and legumes beans split bees chickpeas
and lentils
let me end with a quote from dr dean
ornish about the annals meat papers that
suggested people should continue to eat
meat was abandoned his lifestyle heart
trial was one of the many studies the
meat panel ignored it showed that a
plant-based diet and lifestyle program
could reverse the progression of even
severe coronary heart disease the number
one killer of men and women the control
group actually made modest reductions in
meat comparable to those in the annals
review and show continued worsening of
their atherosclerosis
take solace ornish said in knowing that
the light drives out the darkness
but these days
the light has to be very bright indeed
caveat emptor
don't be fooled
your life may depend on it
[Music]
you